We're going to continue where we left off in caching and we're going to look at a lot of interesting
design decisions.
Let me reduce this a little bit.
Is it better?
Let's echo maybe, maybe a little bit more.
How about now?
OK, a little bit better.
Let's stay like this for a while.
Maybe that's even better.
OK, people can still hear me in the back, right?
All good.
OK, so we're going to go more into caching.
This is an important topic because locality is very strong in programs as you have been exposed to
last time.
Like locality is a very strong and a lot of things we do right.
One of the things that Mohammed gave as an example of locality, like temporal locality is you're
probably sitting in a, well, spatial locality is you're probably sitting in the same place you were
sitting before, right?
That's true.
And you're sitting together with similar people.
That's kind of spatial locality, right?
The temporal locality is you kind of basically come back every time around the same time.
So that's the temporal locality aspect.
So I can actually exploit both types of locality.
And this exploitation has been very strong in programs.
It's a property of programs.
And as a result, most of our systems are dedicated to caches.
Today's now we're going to deconstruct that later on.
Is this the right way of building systems?
It's always good task.
Can we do better?
And the answer is maybe we have lots of cache in our systems because we're not doing things right,
because we're basically moving data a lot across the memory hierarchy from the process, from the
storage system to the processor.
If you actually do computation much closer to memory units, maybe we don't need to move that data.
So it's good to think about that.
But that's not how things evolved so far.
That's what we would like things to be evolving into the future so that we save a lot of energy as
well.
But let's get started.
Actually, I'll give you another example of locality principle that was violated.
I was in the US for a conference recently.
I was supposed to arrive yesterday, the previous day, but I arrived yesterday, unfortunately.
And one of the reasons was, well, there are multiple reasons I was supposed to fly from Atlanta to
Chicago and then Chicago to Zurich.
First of all, I should have done better.
I should have flew directly from Atlanta to Chicago to Zurich.
But OK, there may be reasons why not to do that.
And then weather appeared in Chicago, thunderstorms, so I couldn't go to Chicago.
They put me on another flight, which is supposed to be safe, meaning going from Atlanta to
Washington, DC OK, that sounds good, right?
I was pretty happy.
I will go to Washington, DC and then come to Zurich.
Now, the problem is they didn't really follow the principle of locality when they were scheduling
planes.
So the plane that was supposed to go from Atlanta to Washington DC was coming from Chicago.
I couldn't make it because there's weather in Chicago, right?
So I can see that.
And then I had to actually fly to New York and etcetera.
In the end, in the end, I did fly, but one day later.
The issue is if they actually kind of partitioned the country a little bit, I'm not going to tell
you the name of the air airline partitioned the country and actually exploited locality within
those partitions and never actually, let's say, connected planes across the entire country.
They could have actually done a much better job in scheduling in my opinion.
I know there's a lot of other things that they need to take into account in scheduling things, but
if you actually localise communication as much as possible, in this case, communication is where
you route the planes, right?
If you don't route unless you absolutely need it across a bigger global space, if you keep it local,
you can actually optimize for other unpredictable events as well more easily if every plane goes
through Chicago, for example.
If you've done that routing that way, then you're in big trouble basically, and everybody who
depends on you is in big trouble also.
So I thought I could spin this as a.
Locality principle, and you can see that it's a locality principle.
Actually, there's another principle over here which is minimising communication as much as possible.
That's going to be very important.
Also, if you minimise communication across the systems you design, you can in general do better
because long distance communication is almost always much more expensive than short distance
communication.
That's true for planes, that's true for circuits also.
Basically minimise communication, minimise movement in general.
OK, so that's the benefit of caches.
Basically they exploit locality principle really well when locality principle exists and then
locality exists in programs and they also minimise communication.
But maybe there is a broader aspects that minimises communication.
If you actually can do computation inside the memory inside DM for example, maybe you need less
caches in the processor.
So keep that in mind.
OK, with that, let's get started.
These are some readings that we have that you're familiar with.
This is the memory hierarchy example.
We build these memory hierarchies so that we don't go to memory as much as possible.
The problem is you cannot build something fast and and big.
So you actually progressively build faster and small things and make them bigger and slower and put
them together in a hierarchy.
Then the question is, how do you manage this hierarchy?
So managing this hierarchy has been the subject of many, many works, and there's a lot of work that
has actually got into a processor design.
If you look at a very complex processor design today, there are a lot of algorithms that are used in
managing the cache hierarchy.
We're going to touch the surface of some of them.
There is a whole lot more.
OK, this is another memory hierarchy.
I should also say that memory hierarchy is actually bigger than what was depicted earlier.
Basically, you have a single machine.
Single machine can host a lot of memory today, especially terabytes and terabytes and terabytes.
But even that's not enough for some workloads that we have today.
Very large workloads like AI training data or some other workloads like data centre workloads, then
you need actually multiple machines.
What we actually do is memory extend the memory hierarchy beyond a single machine.
You may have some compute nodes where you do computation and you have a local memory hierarchy and
you may connect very large memories to it.
These are called memory nodes in data centres and you access remote memory through a low latency
network.
This is how a data centre setting looks like.
And I'll go into a little bit more detail over here.
So this is a system with memory blades.
So you have some computation blades where you have compute and a lot of memory, but that memory is
not enough.
So you actually go off chip or off the blade to some other memory blades.
It could be in some other rack, it could be in the same rack, right?
And this memory blade architecture can differ of course, but it may, it may actually have
lightweight CPUs, memory controllers, etcetera, and lots of memory connected to it.
And the purpose of that is to serve data essentially.
It's good to think about that.
This is the amount of data that we're dealing with today and it's, it keeps increasing basically in
all of the applications.
I've shown you that in lecture one, right?
So you can see that our designs, large scale designs have adapted to storing that data and serving
compute units with that data.
OK, Basically this is part of the memory hierarchy essentially.
And this is local memory that's on the CPU that we're kind of examining.
And this is remote memory.
So if you actually miss in the local memories, you go to the remote memories.
That's actually a longer penalty to access, but that's higher capacity, right?
OK, there's work in this area, including some of the work that we have done a long time ago.
You can take a look at it, but let's get back to our cache example and build up some of the policies
that are employed in real systems today.
So you've seen a direct map cache, you remember it.
Hopefully direct map means a given main memory block can be placed in on one, only one possible
location in the cache, right?
This is very restrictive mapping basically.
And that direct map where exactly a particular block is mapped is based on the physical address of
the block.
And you take, you index the cache using a piece of that physical address that determines which set
you're in and a set of locations, there's only one possible location.
Basically that's the idea of a direct map cache.
Very inflexible.
If two addresses that you're operating on at around the same time happen to map to the same index,
then you're in trouble because you cannot have both of them in the cache, right?
And we solved this problem to by adding set associativity, right?
Set associativity enables the cache or or a single or a given memory block to potentially reside in
two possible locations.
If it cannot go into one of those sets because somebody else is using that location, and that's it,
you can actually put it in some other set.
That's the idea.
OK.
We went through the direct map cache example as you've seen.
And basically we we basically demonstrate the problem.
If we to enable blocks with the same index to map to more than one cache location, you need more
than one location essentially in a given set.
Set is essentially all the blocks with the same index, right?
And of course you can repeat the same exercise, you have only two locations.
But what if you need 3?
Because you may be actually using blocks ABC around the same time and they happen to map to the same
index.
Well, make it three-way associative or four way associative, right?
That sounds good.
What if you need four more than four?
Well, make it even more associative, eight way associative in this case.
In this case, it happens to be, It happens that in our toy cache we had only 8 blocks.
And having eight way associative cache with eight blocks means that essentially you don't need an
index anymore, right?
Because any block can go anywhere in the cache.
So there is no indexing mechanism.
You just basically compare the tags of each block with the tag of the address.
That's the idea.
That's why it's called fully associated.
In other words, every block can, any block can map to any location in the cache, which means by
definition no index bits.
This is the most flexible form, but you can see that this is more expensive because you have more
tag comparisons that you need to do to figure out whether the block that you're looking for is in
the cache or not.
OK, OK, This was the slide where we left off at.
We were talking about associativity and trade-offs.
So degree of associativity is essentially how many blocks can map to the same index or the set.
I've already kind of said this, right?
If you get higher associativity, the hope is that you'll get higher hit rate because you reduce the
situations where you need more places for blocks because the blocks happen to compete with the
happen to have the same index, right?
The downside, of course, as you get slower access time because you have this, let's go back to this
picture.
You have these comparators and you have to do the matching across all of those comparators.
And then there's logic to determine which one matched or whether anyone matched, right?
There's a hit logic.
And then there's also the maxing multiplexing on the datastore side.
Whichever one matched should be multiplexed out correctly, right?
So there's a critical path over here, which is the comparator, the hit miss determination logic and
the maxing logic over here.
So it's a control path essentially.
OK, So you get slower cache access time with higher associativity and you also have more expensive
hardware because obviously we added more competitors, larger tags and larger maxes.
Right now the good news is you don't want all of your caches to be higher associativity because you
also get diminishing returns.
There's a lot of work that analysis performance of caches.
The curve kind of looks like this as you increase the associativity of the cache while you keep the
size constant size meaning one MB cache, you just keep increasing associativity.
Number of blocks is constant, but the associativity increases.
You get into diminishing returns, meaning your hit rate at some point doesn't increase.
And the biggest return is when you move from direct map cache to two, two way associative cache and
then two way to four way, and then four way to eight way.
But once you go from eight way to sixteen way, you get fewer benefits.
You still get some benefits on some workloads depending on what workload you have, but still the
curve looks like this.
OK, so ideally you need to determine the associativity of your cache.
And we're just talking about one cache, right?
Imagine that you're doing this optimization for five different levels of caches, and it's not just
associativity.
We'll talk about other things as well.
OK, So hopefully you know the basic concepts.
Let's talk about some issues and set associative caches.
And I will introduce the notion of each block having a priority to continue the discussion, because
this is the more general form of what we're going to discuss.
Basically, each block, we're talking about a single set, right?
Now, in a single set, think of each block having a priority, right?
This indicates how important it is to keep the block in the cache.
And there's a key issue that you immediately face as a cache designer, how do you determine or
adjust these priorities of blocks?
Which block is more important than the other?
And how do I determine that, right?
In a set of cache, this is necessary.
In a direct map cache, there is no choice, right?
You have one block and you replace that, right?
Actually, you do have a choice and the choice is that do you actually want to replace the block
that's already in there or or do or do you want to keep it there and the incoming block, you throw
it away, right?
There's, there's a choice even there, but ignore that for now.
In a set of associative cash, the choice increases and there are three key decisions that you need
to make in a set whenever something happens.
Into the cache, into the set, promotion inside the set, and eviction from the set.
Eviction is a replacement.
Let's take a look at what these are.
Insertion means what happens to the priorities of the blocks inside the set when you put in a new
block, right?
You just fetch the new block that you missed on and you're placing it inside the set.
What happens to the priorities?
Which one should be the highest priority, right?
So where to insert the incoming block?
And then there's whether or not to insert the block over here.
OK, we're going to talk about some policies for this later.
And you can imagine many, many policies, including machine learning based policies that people are
developing a lot today.
Promotion says what happens to priorities on a cache hit, Meaning you have an access, it's hitting
the cache in that set.
Now how do you change the priorities?
Do you increase the priority of the thing that hit?
And what do you do to the priorities of other things, other blocks that are that are mapped in the
same set?
Because you have some new information right now, right?
It's good to think about it.
Also, basically whether and how to change the block priority eviction or replacement means what
happens to priorities on a cache miss, meaning which block do you evict and how do you adjust the
priorities after you do the eviction?
And the hope is that you have encoded your priorities of the blocks and the sets in such a way that
you will evict the lowest priority block, right?
That's the goal because lowest priority should mean something.
This is the block that is basically that I care about the least because maybe the processor is never
going to touch it again, right?
That sounds like a good reason to evict that block, right?
If I have perfect information that the processor is never going to need that block again from the
cache, I should even not put that block in the cache to begin with, right?
That's the idea of a priority.
But if I have very good information that this is the block that the processor is going to touch very
soon again, need very soon again, then maybe I should keep it in the cache, right?
That's the idea.
The question is, how do you actually adjust these priorities?
And you may have guessed existing processors do a lot of prediction for this.
They actually use both predictors that are somewhat similar to branch predictors that we have
discussed.
We're not going to go into a lot of detail, but they also use different predictors here as well.
And the prediction is essentially A locality prediction mechanism.
How do you predict the locality of the block that you're accessing?
But there's other aspects to it also, like the cost of a block, because locality is 1 aspect.
Am I going to access this block soon again?
And the other aspect is if I'm going to access this block at some point, maybe not so soon, maybe
not so many times, how long is it going to take for me to get the block from wherever it resides,
right?
If it's, if it's going to take ages to get the block again because it's somewhere far away in remote
memory, maybe I should keep it in the cache so that I don't pay that cost again.
And maybe I evict something that I'm going to get more easily in the future, right?
So there's a lot of decisions, there's a lot of information that you can use to actually make a
decision here.
OK, but let's take a look at some of these things that people use, at least the initial ones.
We're not going to go into the very, very, let's say heavyweight researchy wants that are used in
real processors.
So the first question is which block in the set to replace on a cache miss.
If there's an in Valve block, that's a good one to replace right?
In Valve means that block is not occupied right now.
If all are valid, then we consult what is called the replacement policy and people have invented a
lot of replacement policies.
1 is random.
You choose randomly which block to replace, right?
You have 4.
Let's say you have four way associative cache and you need to choose one of them to evict.
You can basically flip a random number generator and the random number generator says wait 3.
That sounds kind of stupid because it's not using any information about the program or any
prediction from the past.
But in some cases this may not be a bad idea either, right?
Depends on your access patterns.
There is an access pattern, for example, that thrashes the set.
We're going to talk about that.
Thrashing the set means you have four way associativity, but you need 60 ways of associativity.
If you choose randomly, you're not going to do as bad basically, and you may get lucky.
OK, we're going to talk about that.
Another thing could be 5, four first and first out.
That's another policy.
If your access pattern like is like this, that may not be bad, but it turns out many programs access
patterns are not first and first out.
So that's actually usually a very bad policy.
Least recently used is a very commonly used policy because essentially programs are based on loops
and they keep repeating the same pattern access pattern in the in a broader structure you're
accessing for.
For example, blocks ABCDABCDABCDABCD repeatedly, right?
So if you this is called the cyclic reference pattern.
So if you actually evict the least recently used block, then the probability that you're going to
keep something useful in the cache is high.
That's the idea, assuming that access pattern holds, right?
That's not always the case, but people use the least recently used policy because it's better than
many other policies.
It turns out it's not.
Well, depends on the cache design, but random is not that bad either.
By the way, OK, least recently used, as we will see, is not easy to implement, especially when your
associativity is high.
Start thinking about this.
If you have a 32 way associative cache, how do you keep track of the least recently used block?
Right, I'll let you think about that because we're going to get get to that exercise soon.
That's why people actually use approximations.
The least recently used, for example, not most recently used.
One of them not most recently used means don't evict the most recently used block.
The block that the processor needed most recently.
Probably the processor is going to need again, protect it, but choose randomly among the other ones,
for example.
Frequency is another aspect that we haven't talked about in this particular slide yet.
What about frequency of access?
Maybe something is going to be the least recently used, but something else is going to be very
frequently used into the future.
How do you take that into account?
Well, you need to keep some counters that predict frequency of access, right?
So people actually have implemented frequency based policies also, as well as recency based policies
and combinations of those also.
So you can see that there are multiple aspects to replacement policy.
And all of these apply to anything other than direct map caches.
We discussed these costly to refresh earlier.
We're going to get back to that.
Why would memory access have different costs?
I've given you just one example, remote memory, local memory, but it could be also the fact that you
have many levels of cache hierarchies and your block that you're evicting resides far away in the
cache hierarchy and some other thing that you're considering to evict resides close by.
OK, there could be bank conflicts, etcetera inside the bank.
OK, we're not.
We're going to get back to this also.
And a lot of processors today use some sort of hybrid replacement policies, actually, meaning a
single algorithm, just like we did see in branch prediction doesn't work very well for all access
patterns.
So why don't you combine different types of algorithms or prediction mechanisms to decide what to
evict?
This is the hybrid replacement policy.
Then we're going to see some examples of that.
We're going to talk about optimal replacement policy also, but you can start thinking about that.
OK, LRU least recently used.
This is very by by far the most common policy that you will see in caching literature.
Pieces of this exist in many parts of the cache hierarchy in existing processors, including cutting
edge ones.
And the idea here is to evict the least recently accessed block, right?
The problem is immediately you need to keep track of access order of blocks.
If you want to know perfectly which ones the least recently accessed block, you need to really have
a idea of which ones are accessed in which order.
You can keep time stamps for that.
For example, it'll be extremely costly to have a time stamp for a cache block, right?
Then you run into whenever you keep time stamps, you run into how do I what happens when I overflow
the time stamp right?
So it's good to think about that.
So OK, let me ask you the question.
If you have a two way associative cache, meaning two blocks in one set, how many bits do you need to
identify the least reasonably used block in that set?
This is not a trick question.
What is the minimum number of bits anybody can venture out?
No.
Yes, one, exactly.
The minimum number of bits is 1 basically.
So you have two choices and you can encode 2 choices with one bit, right, Because 2 to the one is
well, yeah, one bit basically can encode zero or one.
And if it's zero way, zero is the least recently used.
If it's one way, one is the most least recently used.
And by definition, the other one is the most recently used, right?
So you need only one bit.
OK, let's make this slightly harder.
You have a four way associative cache, four blocks.
What do you what, what storage do you minimally need to keep the ordering of the blocks of those
four blocks?
Perfect ordering.
Now this is sounding more like a probability course actually in probability, of course, I think they
should have the this sort of applications because it's actually a very good application of
probability and statistics.
Five.
OK, how did you get to 5?
OK, that sounds good.
So you even chucked that from me.
You didn't do it for the Chuck that that's good, but you still win it basically.
That's the right answer.
So you have 4 possibilities, right?
Essentially, the first block location way 0, actually one of the ways, one of the four ways can be
the most recently used.
The remaining three ways could be the next recently used.
The remaining two ways could be the next next recently used.
And the last one has one choice.
So the first one has four choices, the second one has three choices, the third one has two choices,
and the last one has one choice.
And it's multiplicative, basically the number of choice you have.
So it's really 4 factorial different orderings that you can have in a four way cache, in a 32 way
cache.
That's 32 factorial basically.
And we know that 32 factorial is a huge number.
4 factorial is not that bad, but it's still a lot of bits, right?
You said 4 factorial is well, it's for 24 options, so it's really log 2 to the 24 bits, which is
really 5 bits saying quote.
But this is actually complex.
Also, it's not just the storage.
Well, I, I think we've already said this.
How many different access orders are possible?
How many bits needed to encode?
So 5 is the right answer.
But then there's also logic to determine this, right?
So we need to have some encoding logic and decoding logic to do this, right?
OK, you can do the number for a 32 factorial.
And that's exactly why people don't implement perfect LRU in real systems.
There are four way you can get away with it.
OK, as N increases, the complexity of this becomes insurmountable.
You don't want to keep track of this perfect.
So as a result of this, most modern processors do not implement true LRU or perfect LRU that keeps
perfect ordering of the blocks in highly associated cache essentially.
So there clearly we said this, but there's another reason which is LRU is an approximation right to
predict locality anyway.
Meaning this is if you perfectly determine what should be evicted, assuming least recently used,
you're not going to get a high hit rate necessarily.
In fact, your program may be behaving completely oppositely to LRU, and then you'll get 0% hit rate,
right?
So you should be careful.
And there's no reason to actually dedicate a whole lot of resources for something that you don't
know is going to work very well.
OK, so a lot of processors actually do not MRU, for example, not existing processors in the past.
Some of them you use I'm, I'm not going to go into the details of this, but some of them use
hierarchical RU.
Basically divide the N way set into some groups, track the MRU group and the MRU way in each group,
which is clearly not ordering information, but some notion of MRU in in each group most recently
used.
They do also some other things like victim, next victim MRU and next MRU maybe, but I will not go
into details.
Basically that's there's a lot of basically poor man's LRU approximation algorithms that people have
developed in the past for the reasons that that are basically outlined here.
True LRU is complex and maybe that's not really what you want.
OK, so let's talk about LRU versus random a little bit because this is interesting I think.
So you have a four way cache.
Let's say you have cyclic references to blocks ABCDE.
If you have LRU policy, you get 0 percentage rate, right?
Hopefully you convince yourself that way whenever you access, let's say you, you do this
referencing.
Whenever you access E, you're going to evict D, right?
Whenever you access A, you're going to evict EI guess.
And you keep doing that.
Basically you'll get 0 percentage rate.
Makes sense hopefully because you're thrashing the set.
This is exactly an example of thrashing the set and LRU is bad.
OK, when the program working set in a set is larger than the set associatively, that's called
thrashing.
Now if you use LRU policy, you get 0%.
If you use some other policy, you'll get better than 0% hopefully.
And random replacement is actually better when this sort of thrashing occurs.
For example, I'll let you do the calculations here because it requires a little bit more probability
in this case.
But if you have a random number generator and if you decide to evict one of those four things that
are in the cache, what is the hit rate that you will get right?
You can do that study on your own.
Could be a good exam question or maybe a good, good work homework question.
I actually think it's a good applied probability and statistics kind of question.
But basically you can see that the random replacement is not bad because it's likely that it's not
going to evict consistently the one that's going to give.
0% hit rate, you will keep some blocks in the cache.
For example, I'll give you another replacement policy, in this case, not random.
You always keep ABCD in the cache and forget about E You get an 80% hit rate with that policy,
right?
That sounds very good.
It's not random.
You may call it's not a good policy, but in this case, it's a very good policy compared to LRU,
right?
And random will be somewhere in between and I'll let you figure that out.
So in practice, basically the performance of the replacement policy depends on the workload.
And it turns out average hit rates.
These are studies that were done earlier.
This has to be repeated for workloads, of course, but average a trade off across many, many, many,
many workloads that people have examined in small caches.
Random and LRU are similar, which is surprising to me, which was very surprising when I learned
this.
But they do cater to different workloads.
So having a hybrid of LRU and random is not a bad idea, for example, because they cater to different
access patterns.
When you're thrashing, use random or something even more intelligent.
When you're not thrashing and LRU is somewhat working, predict that and use LRU type replacement.
OK, so that's one of the best of both worlds type of policies.
Then the question becomes, how do you actually decide what policy to use in branch predictors?
We had a meta predictor, if you remember right, that decides, oh, this predictor is doing well for
this branch.
This other predictor is doing well for this other branch.
So I'm going to predict that and use the predictor that the branch is being likely to be predicted
better with, right.
We can do the same thing.
It turns out we have introduced a way of doing that in cache as I'm going to talk about this paper
for some other reason later on.
And the idea is to sample which set needs what kind of policy and you can decide the policy on a per
set basis or on a per global cash basis.
We're going to get back to that later on.
Any questions?
It's fun, right?
OK, let's talk about the optimal replacement policy because people have been concerned about this a
lot, starting with Beldi who was at IBM and they introduced this OPT optimal policy and they, their
definition is an optimal cash replacement policy replaces the block that's going to be referenced
furthest into the future by the program.
OK, that sounds good, right?
And this is something that has been introduced and a lot of people think it's optimal.
Maybe it's optimal with some optimal.
Optimal is a very dangerous word to use.
Whenever I see optimal in a paper, I basically say optimal under what conditions, right?
Because you got to specify the conditions under a policy or something is optimal.
And clearly this can be optimal under some conditions.
But what is it optimal for?
This is actually optimal for minimising miss rate.
Again, under some conditions, maybe it's it doesn't assume, for example, you can bypass the cache,
right?
If you bypass the cache for some blocks, meaning you don't place the block inside the cache, then
you actually violate some of the optimality conditions.
But assume that you don't do that.
This is actually optimal for minimising the miss rate.
You can convince yourself of that.
It's not a bad definition.
Unfortunately it's not optimal for minimising execution time because what it doesn't consider is
what I just told you earlier, which is the cost of a mess.
How costly is it to re fetch a block?
Right?
Maybe the block is going to be the furthest to be referenced in the future by the program, but it's,
it's going to take me like 10 seconds to fetch it because it's going to come from far away.
Whereas all of the other blocks are going to take me 10 nanoseconds to fetch.
I'd rather keep that block that's going to be referenced furthest into the future if I take time or
cost of access into account, right?
So that's why this policy is very interesting for some purposes, but for some other purpose in
modern memory hierarchies, this policy breaks down very badly actually.
And I will show you even a simpler example than this very exaggerated numbers later on.
There's also another question.
How do you implement this policy?
Clearly this requires you to look into the future, right?
And I have not figured out how to look into the future yet.
If you have, please let me know or actually start a company and maybe you can fool some people.
That's good.
It's implementing it is impossible.
How Assimilating it is hard also, right?
So if you want to simulate this policy and basically you design A simulator and you want to compare
your own policy to the optimal policy, even that is difficult because that requires you to look
into the future and you need to actually have multiple passes over the program.
It's a very dynamic problem based.
I'll let you think about that also.
There are a lot of these interesting issues and simulation also and and when the system becomes more
complex, simulation becomes more complex, OK.
I've already said a lot of these.
We're going to talk about MIS overlapping later on, but the the cost of a cache miss varies from
block to block because it depends on where the where you would refresh the block from and how
costly is it to the processor?
Does it make the process stall, for example?
It's good to think about that.
OK, we're going to get back to that.
So this is some recommended reading, and in this work it shows that there are some misses that are
most more costly than others because their latency is exposed at stall time.
So reducing the miss rate is not always good for performance.
By reducing the miss rate, you can actually hurt performance, which sounds unintuitive, but if you
actually know what's going like what's going on underneath, it's very intuitive.
OK, let's talk about some other things before we go into more sophisticated policies.
So we've seen A tag store and we've seen what components there are inside it, right?
We need a valve bit.
That valve bit specifies whether that tag store houses a block from the main memory.
If the valve bit is set, then you need to have A tag that specifies part of the address that needs
to be matched to declare a hit.
And you need to have some replacement policy bits, assuming it's not a direct map cache, right?
And we've seen the replacement policy bits, let's talk about some other bits.
And this is going to cause some other issues.
Actually it's the other way around, but I like thinking about it this way.
For example, some caches, cache blocks have dirty bits or modified bits.
It's the same meaning when you modify something, you make it dirty and you need to deal with it
later on.
Later on.
Modify means store when you store a different value to a block.
You said a bit saying I stored a different value to this block.
So when it's being replaced from the cache, be careful because I modified this block in the cache
and it didn't get modified in the later caches and also a main memory.
So the replacement logic needs to take this into account and the when the block is evicted, it needs
to write the block back to the next level or to main memory basically somewhere it needs to work so
that you don't lose that update, right?
That's the idea of a modified or dirty bit.
OK, then the question also is a bigger question actually, do you really need this bit even?
That's a question, right?
So basically the bigger question is how do you handle writes or stores to a block in your cache?
When do you write the modified data in a cache to the next level?
So write through means at the time the write happens, maybe meaning whenever you're writing to the
cache, you write to the next level, and also the next level and also next level.
Eventually memory.
Basically your stores get propagated across the memory hierarchy.
So you don't need a bit saying that, oh, this block is modified so you need to write it later on
because you've already written that Write back means when the block is evicted, meaning modify the
block only in this cache and then wait until it's evicted to write it to the next level in the cash
hierarchy and clear, there are trade-offs associated with it, right?
Write back cash.
Actually, let's do everything over here.
Write through cash is simpler.
You don't need this additional bit saying I modified this block, right?
It sounds nice.
Also, there are other benefits to this.
All levels are up to date and consistent.
We're going to talk about something called cash coherence.
Have you Have you heard of cash coherence before?
Maybe somehow, basically this issue happens when you have multiple processors and when multiple
processors access the same cache block, they should get the most up to date data, right?
That's the idea over here.
And if you actually write the data to all of the caches, they will have access to that most up to
Now the downside is if you keep writing, sending your rights every time to the next level, next
level, next level main memory, then you're really consuming a lot of bandwidth, right?
So we don't want to be doing that.
You're losing some of the benefits of caching that block.
Basically.
That's the idea.
And the main reason is you're really not combining rights.
So when you write to a cache block, when the processor writes to a cache block is it turns out there
is something called right locality.
Also, you write to it again and again and again and again and again.
If that happens, for example, if you're writing to NRA, my favorite example is writing to NRA.
You have a 64 byte cache block.
You're doing 4 byte writes and the processor is really writing the data into NRA.
That's 16 writes going to the same cache block, right?
If you actually have a write back cache, you'll write.
Back to the next level only once.
Hopefully if you have a right through cache, you'll write to the next level and the levels after
that 16 times.
So you will not be able to take the opportunity to reduce bandwidth by 15 out of 16 with your cache.
So this is an argument against right through caches.
And this is exactly why right through caching is not used in many levels, except if you're somewhat
tightly coupled in between L1 and L2 close to the processor, for example.
Sometimes they to make coherence easier, they use write through caches at that level.
OK, so it's good to think about these trade-offs.
These are very good questions.
But these today imagining for example, having a write through L5 cache or L4 cache is unreasonable
because you don't want to write anything to memory.
OK, OK.
So the the benefit of write back cache is essentially you can combine multiple writes to the same
block before it gets evicted.
Keep that example of 16 writes that you're doing to every four byte of the block.
And this potentially saves bandwidth between cache levels.
It also saves energy today.
The downside is of course now you need to have a bit in the tag store indicating the block is dirty
modified.
OK, that's not that's the least of our concerns actually.
We'll add a lot more bits as you will see soon.
OK, there's another question with writes actually, which is which could be applied to anything.
Initially people applied this to blocks that you're writing to, but this is actually more general.
The question is basically, do we allocate a cache block on a write miss, meaning the processor is
doing a store, it misses the cache.
And should we bring the data, the entire cache block from memory and put it inside the cache or
should we not allocate?
This is different from write back and write through, right?
Because the block that you're writing to may be in the cache.
Then you have to make a decision.
Do I write to the next level as well?
That was the write back and write through.
Write allocate and not allocate is I have a cache miss.
It's requested by a store instruction, not a load instruction.
Do I bring the block into the cache?
Right?
So if you allocate on a write miss, OK, you can combine writes instead of writing each individually
to the next level.
That's good.
You can combine writes to the to essentially the same block.
This is also simpler because write misses can be treated the same way as read misses.
You don't need to do anything special for writes or stores.
Now this requires a transfer of the whole cache block, right?
That's the downside if you don't allocate.
This conserves cache space if locality of written blocks is low, so it gives you a potentially
better cache rate.
OK, so you may say why would the locality of written blocks would be low?
And then the question is, yeah, I don't know if there's a good reason for it, but I'll give you one
reason, which is what I show what I discussed earlier.
You're doing streaming writes.
You basically start from, you have a 64 byte block and you're going to write to the 1st 4 bytes and
then the next four and the next 4 and you have 16 bytes.
The processor is going to do 16 bytes, 16 writes to a 64 byte block.
If the processor is going to reconstruct the cache block anyway, why do you bring the cache block to
the cache from memory in the 1st place?
That's the idea.
Basically, you're going to overwrite everything in the cache block, so don't bring it in the first
place, right?
You would say 1 memory access that.
So that's the idea.
That's one good example of why it may not make sense to allocate a cache block, meaning bring it
from main memory to the cache.
OK.
But as I said, it's more it's, it's different.
And this, this question can be generally applied right?
Meaning do we allocate a cache block on any miss, forget about load and store?
Because some cache blocks may be reused later on, some cache blocks may not be reused later on.
And a lot of processors actually make that decision today as opposed to making a right specific
decision.
Is the block that I'm going to fetch going to be useful for me in the future?
And if you make that decision very nicely, very cleanly, you'll save a lot of bandwidth either by
not transferring the block that you're not going to use in the future and just transferring a piece
of it that you really need, or maybe no part of it because you're going to overwrite the entire
thing.
Or by transferring the block and actually making a lot of use of it inside your cache.
So that's the idea.
OK, so this is the scenario that we're going to discuss a little bit because this has enabled caches
to be sectored as I will describe.
What if the processor writes to an entire block over a small amount of time?
Is there any need to bring the cache, bring the block into the cache from the memory in the 1st
place?
I've already said no.
Then the question becomes.
How do you treat that cache block right?
Why do we not simply write the data to only a portion of the block?
We're going to introduce the sub block notion, which is used in many, many caches.
When caching was first employed by IBM, for example, they use a sub block cache in 1960s and they
still use sub block caches, which is a very good idea for the reasons that we will see.
So for example, you're going to write only four bytes out of the 40 into the 64 byte block.
Why don't you just write those 4 bytes and designate everything else around it as invalid?
That's the idea.
The problem is now you're violating kind of the block abstraction.
The abstraction of the block is at 64 bytes.
I keep a single tag, single valid bit, single dirty bit for all 64 bytes.
If I'm going to write only to 4 bytes of it without having the data for any of the rest, I need to
modify this abstraction.
I can still keep the tag on a block basis, but I need to do something with the valid and dirty bits
right?
And this is what I will do.
Basically the idea is to have a sub blocked or sector cache.
Divide a block into sub blocks or sectors and the idea is to have separate valid and dirty bits for
each sub block or sector.
You still have the same tag for the entire block and you allocate only a sub block or a subset of
sub blocks on a request.
Now this gives you a little bit more flexibility in your caching, and the big advantage is no need
to transfer the entire cache block into the cache.
If you're going to write to a sub block 2, make it valid, make it dirty.
Everything else stays invalid and not dirty, and you have a valid bit for the entire thing.
If you really need it, you don't.
You don't necessarily need it, but it may make some hit logic easier.
You you still have the tag.
Hopefully that makes sense.
Right?
So a write simply validates and updates a sub block.
You don't need to access memory.
Now this also gives you another thing which is more freedom in transferring sub blocks into the
cache.
A cache block does not need to be in the cache fully right?
And this enables a lot of potential optimisations that you may want to do.
For example, you can say, OK, this was originally developed for writes, but I can use this for
reads.
Also when I actually am reading from some location main memory, I basically have a predictor that
says oh, fetch sub blocks 05 and six, but not the other ones because I didn't think I, I don't
think I'm going to use it in the future based on my past experience.
So it can bring based on your prediction mechanisms, only the things that you need because now your
cache structure supports it, right?
OK, so the downside of these caches in general, they're more complex, more valid and dirty and
modified bits.
But a lot of caches actually use this sort of sector design today.
And of course, if you don't have a smart prediction mechanism like I described, you may not be able
to exploit spatial locality fully, right?
Because you only deal with sub blocks, right?
Of course, you can use the structure to always bring the cache block when you don't know, you don't
have information.
So you don't lose anything except for some space and some logic complexity for valid and dirty
identification.
OK, let me finish this and then we'll take a break.
So instruction versus data, we didn't talk about that also, but this is also a very important design
decision.
These have different access patterns and characteristics.
So do you keep instructions and data in the same cache or do you separate them?
This is very actually interesting system design decision.
If you actually unify things such that you keep both instructions and data in the same cache, you
can basically enable dynamic sharing of the same cache space.
So it's better overall utilisation and essentially you don't over provision cache space.
Hopefully if you had separate Ind cache.
For example, if you have a 64 KB instruction cache and a 64 KB data cache, and your instructions
need only four kilobytes because you have a very small programs running in general, but your data
needs 124 kilobytes, your instruction cache is heavily underutilised, whereas your data cache is
too small.
Because you dedicated the 128 kilobytes to two different caches, half of it cannot be used by data.
If you had a unified cache, that's 128 kilobytes.
You have 4 kilobytes of instructions and 124 kilobytes of data.
Hopefully they will live nicely together and you will never get a cache miss.
That's the hope.
So that's the beauty of unified caches in general.
If you have better dynamic utilisation, static partitioning, whenever you statically partition
things in general, you run into the problem of under utilisation, right?
OK, so the downside of course is instructions and data can evict or trash each other because there
is no guaranteed space for either if you unify the space.
OK.
So there's another downside, which is probably the biggest downside for unified instruction and
data, and that's the pipeline structure.
Remember the designs that we had for pipelines, you fetch instructions here and you execute
somewhere here.
This is actually pretty far away in terms of the layout.
So they're in different parts of the pipeline, right?
If you actually have a unified cache, where do you place this?
It becomes a placement problem.
If you actually separate the caches instruction here in the fetch engine and data caches in the
memory access engine, you have a much easier routing and interconnect problem that will also make
your cycle time and timing and verification all of those much nicer.
So this is that's why this is very important.
And as a result of this, first level caches are almost always partitioned, meaning split, not
unified pipeline constraints.
This is actually a bigger principle, right?
If for your first level caches are really tightly integrated into the pipeline, right?
Their goal is to serve the data as fast as possible, but you cannot make them too high capacity or
unify things that are supposed to be at different parts of the pipeline to get higher frequency
because they affect your frequency significantly.
OK, all three level caches, L2 cache, L3 cache, L4 cache, they're almost always unified.
They're exceptions.
Some processors, for example, has L had L2 caches, L2 data cache, and L2 instructing caches.
But most of the time the design decision is such that they're unified.
They have both instructions and data for dynamic sharing of cache space essentially.
And also they're not tightly integrated into the pipeline.
You can have some more flexible interconnects at higher latencies to access a bigger cache as
opposed to splitting them across the pipeline.
OK.
Maybe I should really stop here.
We're going to start here.
I was hoping to get to that that next stage, but we're not there yet.
So let's take a break until 1518 and then we'll continue with more cash design decisions.
Na.
OK, which was this slide we talked about instruction versus data and when to unify them and when to
not.
This generally ties into multi level cash management.
Essentially today we have many, many levels of caches and the level of the cache greatly effects how
you design it and what kind of decisions you make.
First level caches, instructions and data are actually very much constrained by their integration to
the pipeline.
The decisions you make in first of all caches are affected by cycle time and the pipeline structure.
As a result, they're very latency critical.
They need to be small, they're usually lower associativity.
And you want to get the hit or miss signal as soon as possible because you need to schedule
instructions, meaning a lot of processors today do out of order dynamic scheduling as we have
discussed in earlier lectures.
And you need to deal with how to schedule loads and stores, right.
And to be able to properly schedule dependent instructions on loads, you need to get the hit miss
signal from the cache accurately.
And if that signal takes a long time, then you have a problem basically.
So I will leave it at that.
But the complexity in that part of the processor is actually quite high in terms of how you actually
schedule loads and stores and also because of the importance of getting the data as well as the hit
miss signal as fast as possible.
Tax store and data store access are usually happen.
They, they're usually performed in parallel.
While you're doing the tax store access, you also start the data store access.
Clearly for the data that you get to be valid, your tax store needs to provide a hit, right?
But you do those concurrently.
OK, Second level caches are less integrated with the pipeline.
As a result, their decisions are much less affected by the pipeline.
But they the decisions that you make in how to manage them need to balance hit rate and access
latency.
If you make them too large, the latency would be very large.
If you make them too small, you go, you won't get a very good hit rate.
So usually they are large, well clearly larger than the first level caches and highly associative.
And latency are is not as important.
And as you go further and further away from the processor, the latency becomes less and less
important.
You really are optimising for hit rate in the end.
And also with larger caches, the tax store and data store or far away caches, tax store and data
store access can be, can happen serially.
And the reason is to save energy in this case, because if you actually are accessing the data store
for every access you make and you don't know whether you're going to hit in the data store, what
happens is you're firing up all the waste and the entire array structure in the data store.
And that's a lot of energy that you spent.
In the end, you're going to get only one piece of one block.
And it's not clear if you're going to get that block either, right?
So if you actually serialise, if you first do the tag store access and you know whether it's a hit
or miss, if it's a miss, you're not going to access the data store, right?
You saved a lot of accesses or misses.
If it's a hit in the tax store, now you know exactly which way the data is in the data store because
that's part of your tax store access.
You know which way matched in the set, so you only access that way in the data store as opposed to
accessing all of the ways in the set.
So you save energy in both ways.
You don't access data store for misses and you access only what you really need on a in a case of
hit.
So that's what serial access to tags and data store can provide.
But first of all, it's not a good idea to do this because it increases your latency because it
serialises tag and data store access.
So as you go further from the processor, access energy is a larger problem due to the size of the
cache.
And the reason you have very large cache is to get high hit rates so that you don't go to memory,
which is even worse.
So tags and data store access are usually usually performed serially.
OK.
There are more design decisions that you have when you actually do multi level caches.
One of the design decisions is first level, for example, it sees all of the accesses that are coming
out of the processor, all load store accesses.
So there's a lot of information.
It's throughput needs to be high.
So it's locality characteristics that it's exploiting is really all of the accesses.
But the next level, second level gets accesses that are filtered by the first level.
So it's good to consider this.
So the second level, the policies that you employ, the predictors that you employ in the second
level should not be the same as the policies that you employ in the first level because they see
complete different access patterns.
And as you go further and further away from the processor, the access patterns are even more
different.
Unless you do completely random access for example, then everybody sees the same access pattern
because caching is useless, right?
If you do completely random, truly random accesses, caching should not provide you any benefits,
right?
So you can get rid of all of your caches.
But we don't have completely random access in our programs.
Although some very large scale applications may look like a lot of the access patterns are quite
random over there.
OK, So it's good to consider this basically.
So existing processors have different policies to cater to different kind of access patterns at
different levels of caching.
OK, there's another thing that I wanted to talk about which is not done as much, but it's good to
consider some things because we're going to do a part of it later on.
So do you access the level serially or in parallel?
Meaning if you do it in parallel, next level cache is accessed in parallel with the previous level,
right?
There's a form of speculative access.
You're basically saying, I don't know if I'm going to hit in this level, so I'm going to start the
access earlier to the next level.
Also, if you do it serially, next level caches cache access only if previous level misses.
So clearly if you do a parallel, you get faster access to data if the previous level misses, but you
also have unnecessary access to the next level if the previous level hits, right?
So there's a trade off latency versus energy and bandwidth serially.
If you do it serially, you get slower access to data if the previous level misses and there's no
wasted access to the next level if the previous level hits.
Then the question is, do you ever want to do a parallel access, right?
And the answer is if you're careful, maybe right.
And also I guess next level does not see the same access as the previous.
We already said a lot of this.
So basically, you may for serial there, there are good reasons for serial, but if you have a good
idea, for example, that you're going to very likely miss this cache, you may want to start your
later accesses, accesses to the next level earlier, right?
So it really depends on what you predict.
An existing process are predictors to decide whether they should access the cache, whether they
should access the next level earlier or later.
Right.
OK, so we talked about a lot of different ideas and complexity without going into the exact design
of the predictors.
Because if you do that, then instead of being a computer architecture course, this will be a cache
architecture course.
That's probably not so let's say efficient in terms of where you are in your education level.
Unless you're designing caches, this is not.
This sounds like a funny joke, but caching is so important that the major conference in our field
ISCA International Symposium on Computer Architecture, there were jokes for many years that this is
the International Symposium for Cache Architecture.
I'm one of the jokers because I think there should be much broader topics as opposed to just caches
in a in a major conference like that.
But I think it's good to think about this.
Caching is extremely important and we should keep working on it, but there could be other solutions
to the same problem.
OK, so just to like re motivate you a little bit before we switch topics.
These caches exist in real processors.
For example, there's a 12 MB L2 in this version of Apple M1.
There's a system level cache where they actually can access different compute units like
CPUSGPUSNPUS.
Their AI accelerators actually can access that cache.
They can share data.
There could be other caches.
You can see that these caches occupy a lot of area, also even more area in some cases.
And that's not enough.
People keep adding caches at the 3D level.
Again, the joke is that at some point, people were.
So if you if you lived around 2000, how many people were born after 2000 here?
OK, probably most of you.
How many people were born before 2000?
OK, some people, including a lot of my graduate students over here, but not all of them, maybe.
Yeah.
So if you lived in during the switch between from multicore, single core to multicore, that's when I
was doing my PhD Basically, people were quite excited about multicore until they understood the
software implications.
And the idea was basically, oh, I'm a chip architect.
I don't want to make my process complex because that's too hard, right?
Let me just stamp out more cores, right?
So people were thinking about, oh, let's stamp out more cores, more cores, more cores.
And then they realised if you stamp out more cores and if you get to use them, something else
becomes a huge bottleneck, which is the memory hierarchy.
And they said, oh, OK, we should keep our jobs, so why don't we put more caches also?
So they kept putting more caches.
And this is where we are basically, we have a lot of caches.
This is actually this is a joke, but it's very good technology like AMD added on top of a processor
chip which already has a lot of caches.
They basically put another chip that has a huge cache, essentially SGAM cache, and that's their
technology.
You can read about that.
It's 64 megabytes of L3 cache in five years ago.
And this is the technology basically it's called hybrid bonding.
According to them, they're hybrid bonding, let's say, and they have two chips that are connected
using copper to copper connections that look like this.
That way they can get the data from that cache relatively quickly to the processor chip.
Very interesting technology.
We may get to that when we talk about processing in memory in the last lecture.
OK, so you can see these pictures at some point become boring because most of what we have is
caches.
So you can see some numbers also.
GPUs have a caches also.
In fact, I'll use some of the GPUs over here as examples.
This is an example from NVIDIA 100.
They have special instructions that enable direct copy from their L2 cache to a scratch pad shared
memory, right?
So there you can use special instructions to bypass some of the caches.
So there's there's some level of programmability exposed to the programmer.
So caches are not necessarily invisible to the software because they're so important for
performance.
You may want to expose to the compiler and the programmer such that the compiler programmer can move
the data when they need to to the appropriate place, right?
So there's bypassing that's employed in the cache hierarchy of both general purpose processors as
well as GPUs that look like this.
And you can see some examples of this there direct copy instructions from memory to on chip memory.
And there's also copy instructions between different streaming multiprocessors as you remember the
terminology.
Essentially there's a GPU over here and the GPU connected to each other, let's say, but within the
same chip.
And you can do communication like that.
And the the size of the caches are quite large actually.
You can see 60 megabytes, but they can be larger today.
This is one example from some number of years ago.
OK, so these are real and people need to deal with these decisions.
Let's talk about some more decisions.
Multi level cache design, essentially, which levels do you place a block into?
So I'll give you some examples.
In real processors, you can bypass some caches, but the problem is actually more general, right?
Which levels to evict a block to.
Whenever you're placing a block, you have a choice.
You have 4 levels of caches and maybe some scratch pads.
Scratch pads are essentially caches that are programmed by the programmer.
We talked about that in the previous lecture, Manual versus automatic Management of Cache space.
Essentially, you have a lot of choices to place a block into either automatically or manually,
right?
Manually, it's a very difficult optimization problem, right?
Automatically it's also a very difficult optimization problem that needs to be done by the hardware
designer, right?
Because the hardware designer decides the management of the cache hierarchy.
Similar thing exists over here.
Which level do you evict a block to, right?
Whenever you're evicting block from L1 cache, do you write it to the next level or do you basically
write it directly to main memory?
Do you write it to some other processors memory?
Do you write it to some other processors?
Cache?
It's good to consider these decisions because these are all options that you have basically whenever
you're evicting a block.
And it may make sense depending on the access patterns that you have, all of them at a given point
in time, each of them may make sense.
Right?
OK.
Do you bypass or don't?
Don't bypass some level.
I'll talk about inclusive, exclusive, non inclusive.
This is also somewhat important because it'll tie to coherence.
So inclusive cache means a block in an inner level is always included also in an altar level.
It turns out this simplifies cache coherence because you're guaranteed to have the block.
A block in an altar you're guaranteed to have.
Essentially, you don't need to check all of the caches basically for blocks, right?
If you just, you can just check the altar level, because altar level is a superset of all of the
inner levels, right?
And as you, as you go inside, that superset becomes smaller and smaller.
So it simplifies coherence because if you're looking for some block as another processor, you can
check only the outer level.
Now the downside of inclusive cache is you waste a lot of space, right?
You have a 64 KB L1, you have let's say 256 KB L2.
One fourth of that L2 is replicated in L1 or the other way around.
You can think of it that way.
You wasted a lot of space.
You have 256 KB L2 and you have let's say 16 megabyte L 3.
Some fraction of it is replicated in L2.
OK, exclusive is completely opposite.
A block in an inner level does not exist and should not exist.
In an ultra level this better utilise the space in the entire hierarchy because now you can have the
same size caches, except you never replicate a block in the hierarchy.
That sounds good.
The downside is coherence is more complex in this case because if you're trying to look for a block,
you need to search all of the caches, right?
So people have implemented, implemented exclusive and inclusive policies.
AMD has exclusive policies, for example.
I don't know if they still have, I don't check their latest processors.
But non inclusive is another option, which is basically not restricting yourself.
This is actually the best for the hardware designer in general.
A block in an inner level may or may not be included in an outer level.
This relaxes a lot of design decisions.
A lot of the Intel processors are non inclusive, right?
There's the one of there's another downside to exclusive.
Whenever you evict a block, you need to make sure there's only one copy in the hierarchy, right?
So you need to be careful with what you do.
You cannot just simply replicate a block.
OK, So you can see that there are a lot of design decisions.
I could give you more, but let's switch gears a little bit to talk about cash performance a little
bit more because there's a lot of optimization that you can do on cache performance.
Some of it is affected by a lot of these design decisions that we have.
So we're going to talk about a few of these and especially we're going to examine cache parameters
versus the hit miss rate.
So cache size, this is one of the first decisions that you need to make, right?
We're talking about a single level right now.
Multi level optimization becomes harder.
This is essentially the total data capacity of the cache.
When whenever someone says one MB cache, for example, that doesn't include a data store tag store,
that's just a data store.
OK, so bigger cache, clearly it can exploit temporal locality better.
I'll get to that slide a little bit.
Well, I'll get to this picture a little bit later.
Essentially, if you have too large of a cache, it adversely effects hit and miss latency.
So bigger is slower clearly.
And we knew that if you have too small of a cache, you don't exploit temporal locality well, because
useful data is replaced often.
So you don't want that either.
So working set is the entire set of data the app executing application references within a time
interval.
Ideally you want to match the size of your working set to the cache or vice versa, right?
I say vice versa because if you're a designer, hardware designer, then you would like to accommodate
the working, common, working sets of programs.
But if you're a software programmer, you're given a processor.
You cannot change the size of the cache, sorry.
In some processors, maybe you can if it's reconfigurable, etcetera, but you're given an L1 cache.
How do I optimise my program?
Well, I rewrite my program such that it always sits in the L1 cache as much as possible, right?
Maximise the rate.
So this is actually, it works both ways, right?
When you're designing hardware, you need to think about what are the easiest cache size the
programmer can deal with.
If it's too small, then they're not going to get good miss rates.
Ideally it's huge enough that nobody cares, but we're not going to be in that situation anytime
soon.
That's why we have this huge hierarchy, right?
So this is common.
This is a common picture over here.
As cache size increases, your hit rate increases.
After some point it doesn't increase, it saturates because for example, you have you, you house the
entire working set, for example, in the cache, right?
OK.
So hopefully that's clear.
So benefits of larger caches also widely varies.
It depends on the applications.
So this is 1 application from this paper.
It's a good paper.
It won the micro test of time award last year.
I'd recommend you take a look at it.
This is essentially the size of the cache number of ways from a 16 weight 1 MB L2.
If you have 0A, essentially you don't have a cache.
If you have two ways, this is the miss rate that you have misses per 1000 instructions.
You can see that this application has very low cache utility.
It has almost a flat miss rate curve regardless of the size of the cache.
Why?
The application is streaming through memory streaming, meaning it's basically going through a huge
array, a 1 billion entry array.
Let's say I just made it up and doing something to it, right?
So it doesn't have a lot of locality except for the spatial locality that you get for cache blocks
that you bring in, right?
OK.
Another application has high cache utility over here.
You can see that as cache size increases, your miss rate keeps increasing, reducing.
And another application here has saturating cache utility, meaning as cache size increases your miss
rate floors to 0 and then further caching cache.
If you increase the cache size further, it won't help because your working set fits in the cache,
right?
That sounds good and all kinds of applications exist which is interesting.
The question is how do you deal?
Deal with them.
I'm not going to talk about how do you deal with them, but here you can read that paper for some
ways of dealing with them.
OK, let's talk about block size.
Block size is the data that's associated with an address tag, right?
That's a 64 byte, for example, or 128 byte.
If you have two small blocks, you're in trouble.
If you have two large blocks, you're also in trouble.
This picture shows it for a fixed cache size.
For a given cache size, if you have two small blocks, that means you have a lot of blocks in the
cache.
If you have two large blocks, that means you have fewer blocks in the cache, and both of them are
not good.
I mean, of course there are some applications that would benefit from either of those, but in
general this is the curve you get.
I should also say that block size is not necessarily the unit of transfer between hierarchies.
Sub because of sub blocking.
We've discussed right where a block is divided into multiple pieces.
But let's ignore sub blocking for now.
If you have two small blocks, you don't exploit spatial locality well, because block is really what
exploit the spatial locality, right?
And you also have a larger tag overhead which is not depicted anywhere here.
But that's also a cost.
If you have two large blocks, now you have two few total blocks for a given cache size.
As a result, you do not exploit temporal locality well in this case.
And you need a lot of spatial locality to exploit spatial locality in that large block, right?
Imagine A1 MB cache with A1 MB block.
You have a single block and you really cache A1 MB region.
That's it.
If you're touching anything else beyond that region, it's a cache miss.
You don't want that in general.
OK, And that's also horrible to program for a programmer, right?
You give them a huge block, then you're really asking.
This is the only thing that you can have in your cache, right?
If they need another one MB or a piece of another one MB when they're in trouble, OK, so basically
two large blocks waste cache space and bandwidth and energy if the spatial locality is not high.
That's why block size has not increased that much.
Cache size have been increasing, but block size if you read papers from 1960s sixty 4 bytes.
If you read papers from 2 thousand 2664 bytes, IBM has longer blocks because they have more control
in their software stack, like hundred 28256 byte blocks.
But 64 byte blocks are pretty common.
128 is OK.
If you go beyond that, it becomes more difficult because of what we just discussed.
OK, OK, so large blocks, there's some optimizations that you can do with large blocks, like they can
take a long time to fill into the cache because your buses 64 bits, let's say, and you're
transferring let's say 256 bytes out of a 64 bit bus, main memory bus.
So it takes a long time.
So people do optimization even with a 64 byte block.
Actually existing processors do optimizations like this.
Critical word means fill the cache block, critical word first.
Critical word is the word that's requested by the load that incurred a cache miss.
So bring that first.
For example, a 64 byte block, you have 16-4 byte words and if the processor is accessing #14 bring
#14 first and then stream in the remaining 15, right?
That's the idea over here.
Supply the critical data to the processor immediately so that you can reduce the stall time of the
processor, which makes sense.
And a lot of processors employ this, even though it does add a little bit more complexity to the
system to communicate which one is the critical word all the way to the memory controller.
It's interesting to think about, right?
There's complexity in our systems.
We keep adding more complexity for this sort of optimization, but the reason is it takes you really
want that word so that the processor can keep executing right?
OK, large cache blocks can based plus bandwidth as we've discussed.
And we've discussed an idea to reduce that, divide a block into sub blocks by associating separate
valid and dirty bits for each sub block.
Basically this is the picture over here and we discussed when this usable, but if you do a good
prediction, you could actually make use of a sub block cache very nicely, I think.
OK, associativity, we've already seen this actually, how many blocks can be present in the same
index, same set.
Larger associativity usually leads to a lower miss rate, reduced conflicts because it reduces the
conflicts, conflict misses, but it also leads to higher hit latency and area costs.
We've discussed this at the beginning of this lecture.
Smaller associativity is lower cost, but it's also and also lower hit latency.
It's especially important for L1 caches as we discussed, but usually this is the curve that you get.
As a result, smaller caches are usually or L1 caches are usually less associative.
But as you go to larger caches, they become more and more associative.
Especially if you do serial tag and data access, then you can reduce the cost of the associative,
right?
So whatever we discussed earlier can change the trade-offs a little bit because if you do a serial
tag.
In data access, you don't need.
Let's assume that your cash is 1024 way associative.
You don't need 1024 comparators concurrently, you don't need 1024 entry Max in the data store.
At least in the data store, what you're doing is really accessing only one way right?
So you can reduce the cost significantly.
And there are other tricks you can play with the tag store.
If you can predict, for example, which way your data is going to come from, which a lot of
processors do at the L1 level, they can actually reduce the complexity in your cache as well.
OK, maybe I'll ask you a question here.
Is power of two associated required?
Not a trick question, but it could be construed as so, yes.
OK, exactly.
That's true.
So recall this is your four way associative cache.
We have four blocks per set and we have a four to one multiplexer over here, right?
Basically a power of two associative is not required because you don't need a reason for
associativity to be a power of two.
Like if you look at the structure, nothing basically encodes the way, right?
You have an index which encodes which set.
You have A tag, which is essentially for every block, but there's nothing that specifies the weight,
right?
So you don't address the weights.
You just bring all of the data from the ways and you select the one that you want.
If you have a three-way associative cache, what happens is you have fewer blocks like this, but
you're not using some of the inputs that you have in the multiplexer, right?
That's the idea.
So three-way associative cache exists.
This could be an exam question.
A simple 1.
So eight way fully associated cache looks like this.
Well, you could have easily made it seven way, right?
Why?
Because I didn't have chip area to have eight way.
Why not?
OK, these things exist.
Twelve way associated caches.
This is Intel Lion code.
They decided twelve way was better for them.
Ask them why.
But chip area design choices, how do you lay out the cache such that you get the maximal area in the
given space that is left or that is designed for the cache.
These are very good reasons to have non power off to associativity.
OK, I've also classified the cache misses before we continue.
There's actually a fourth category, which is coherence misses or communication misses more generally
that I'm going to skip.
Yes.
Is that the processors have a cache or other some processors which doesn't really have a cache, I
see have like maybe outside the cache and there, yeah.
Well, you mean processors like ACPU without a cache today?
Yeah, today they don't exist.
No, in the past they did exist, but that was like 40 years ago.
So everybody has a cache because locality is so strong, essentially.
But, and if you want to, but if you do want to experience how not having a cache looks like, you can
at least you used to be able to turn off caching in BIOS in some systems.
You can try to do that and see how long you're going to wait to do anything on your computer.
I don't know if you, has anyone tried that?
I tried that.
It was a bad idea, but I don't know if the if your BIOS exposed that.
You can also turn off some other things like prefetching, which we're going to talk about later on
or used to be able to depending on the BIOS.
OK, so I'm going to classify cache miss.
There are three, three types, four types actually of compulsory capacity conflict.
And this is good for targeting different cache misses and doing cache optimisations.
Understanding the causes of cache misses is important for doing better optimisations.
So compulsory miss is essentially something that you cannot eliminate with caching.
First, reference to an address always results in a miss, right?
Subsequent references to the block should hit in the cache unless the block is displayed from the
cache for the reasons below, so it has its own category.
This is something you cannot eliminate with cache capacity.
Miss cache is too small to hold all needed data with some assumptions.
It's essentially the assumption is that these are the misses that would occur even in a fully
associated cache with optimal replacement of the same capacity, right?
OK, sounds good.
And then there's conflict miss that's defined as any miss that is neither compulsory or capacity,
assuming there's not communication misses which we're not dealing with right now.
OK, So it's good to understand this miss categories because the action you take in fixing the
problem which is miss is always a problem.
Essentially when you heard hear the word miss, it's problem and you want to fix it.
If you want to improve performance and also energy, the question is how do you fix?
It depends on what kind of miss you're dealing with.
So coherence is something that I didn't talk about, but essentially you missed in the cache because
some other processor got the data from your cache and invalidated what you had.
So that's the fourth category which we may talk about.
And that's a complete different problem actually among than these.
OK, so how to reduce each mistype compulsory?
Unfortunately, you cannot reduce it with caching.
Larger blocks can help because if you have a larger block, you may eliminate the cache miss that you
could reduce.
So there's actually something that you can do in caching, but we're going to see something else
which is being much more proactive.
Caching is a reactive approach in the sense that you touch the data, you store it, but what if you
didn't even touch the data yet?
Can can you be more proactive?
Right.
And that's the idea of pre fetching.
And essentially all processors do this.
You know, they anticipate which blocks will be needed soon and they bring the block earlier into the
cache to reduce the compulsory misses.
OK, conflict misses.
Basically more associativity can help.
That's that's the reason why we introduced associativity in the 1st place, right?
We want more associativity is possible.
We want other ways to get more associative without making the cache more associative.
So it's good to think about these and people have introduced a lot of ideas over here that I'm not
going to go into.
A lot of them made their way.
For example, you want to index into your cache not just with bare address fits, but you want them to
go through a function, and that function randomises which address maps to which block.
This is good.
That way you can balance the access across different sets in your cache, as opposed to having one
set that's heavily overloaded.
Basically, you want to reduce set trashing, right?
You can have software hints, you can have victim caches that I'm not going to talk about right now.
Capacity, the way to fix capacity misses.
Utilise cache space better, right?
Keep blocks that will be referenced right or do a better software management.
Divide working set and computations such that each computation set fits into the cache and you, you
don't overload the cache.
Basically that's the idea.
I'm going to show you some examples of this.
So people have developed a lot of techniques to improve cache performance.
We're going to see some of them.
Three fundamental goals exist.
Reduce miss rate, reduce miss latency or miss cost and reduce hit latency or hit cost if that's on
your critical path.
So if you reduce the miss rates, you can reduce performance.
If more costly to refetch blocks are evicted.
We're going to talk about that.
In the end, the above 3 together affect performance, right?
Because reducing mistake is easy.
But then the problem is your hit latency increases, right?
So you got to be very careful.
So people have developed a lot of approaches.
I will go through some of them.
Let me let's let's talk about some software approaches first, because caching is the part where most
programmers try to optimise early on because they know that this makes a huge difference.
So for example, restructuring data access patterns can get you a better cache, iterates,
restructuring data layout.
And compilers do a lot of these optimisations like loop interchange, tiling, blocking, etcetera.
Some of them they do automatically to take advantage of the cache.
Let's take a look at some of them.
So the the first idea is to restructure data layout or data access patterns.
This is a very simple example.
We've seen this before when we talked about vector processing, right?
We talked about erase vectors.
And if you have a vector or array, in this particular case a matrix that's column major XI plus one
J follows XIJ in memory, right?
So you want to access them together to exploit spatial look out.
Whereas XIJ plus one is far away from XIJ because they're essentially in different columns, right?
And we're column major.
So you don't want to access them together.
That's the idea.
Basically, understanding how your data is laid out will enable you to write poor code or change poor
code to better code.
It's very simple.
Basically what we did over here is.
As opposed to accessing things that are far away from each other in main memory, which means that
they're not in the same cache block, they're in different cache blocks.
We basically access things that are close together in main memory, and we did that by basically
doing loop interchange.
What we did is as opposed to going through the inner loop column by column, which are far away from
each other, we go through the inner group row by row, right?
That's the idea.
And you can do this, compilers can do this, and you should.
Now that you've seen the slide, you should never write poor code like that, right?
OK.
There's also another optimization called blocking or tiling, and the idea here is actually more
general.
You divide loops operating on arrays or vectors or matrices into computation chunks so that each
chunk can hold its data in the cache right.
This avoids cache conflicts between different chunks of computation.
So essentially you divide the working set so that each piece of the working set, smaller working set
fits in the cache, right?
I'll give you an example.
It's also called tiling.
And let's take a look at an example.
You can actually see more in our GPU programming lecture, but essentially same, same memory location
I accessed by neighboring threads over here.
And the idea is to have a program that applies a filter on every pixel of an image, right?
So it's a very regular program if you want to take advantage of data reuse, as opposed to operating
on the entire image, you divide the image into sub images basically because the entire image may be
too big for your cache.
Or if you want to fit this in your register file, the entire image may be too big.
Divide the image into smaller sub images into tiles such that they can be loaded into whatever
hierarchy you don't want.
Misses it, right?
In this particular case, shared memory, scratch pad memory, right?
So this is the code essentially to do that.
So that's tiling basically.
Don't operate on the entire grey part, operate on the green part first.
That's the idea.
So I could apply this to matrix multiplication.
Again, I'll go through this relatively quickly because it's the same idea.
You have two input matrices that are in some layout row major.
It doesn't matter in the end.
But if you operate on two big matrices, you'll get a lot of cache misses because they don't fit in
your cache, right?
So this is what we want to do in the end.
We want to multiply them and get C right?
So if you have naive implementation, you get poor cache locality.
But if you actually and the reason is you have consecutive accesses to B that are far from each
other in different cache lines, and every access to B is likely to cause a cache miss.
Now if you reduce your dimensions, meaning operate on a small piece of each matrix or smaller tiles
that fit in the cache, you can keep them in your cache or in the scratch pad memory or in the
register file basically depending on what you're optimising for.
And the idea is you carve out tiles like this that are smaller than the entire matrices and you do
the operations on tiles.
Once you're done with that tile, you move to the next tile.
So that's the idea.
If you need communication inter tiles, then you need to deal with that somehow.
But this gives you a lot of cache locality in the end.
OK, so basically you're multiplying small sub matrices as opposed to the huge matrix that is going
to destroy your cache.
So that's a very effective optimization.
And if you're interested, we have more lectures that talk about this.
Let me give you another one.
OK, this is the only one I'll give and then we'll we'll, we'll stop, we'll continue tomorrow
restructuring data layout.
I'll go through it relatively quickly because hopefully it'll be obvious by now.
We're what we're doing over here is a pointer based traversal of a linked list.
You have a assume that you have a huge linked list and you're searching for a key over there.
1 billion nodes, unique keys.
So we have this code over here and it doesn't have a good cache iterate.
Why?
What?
Because you have some frequently accessed fields.
This while you're going through the linked list, you're accessing every single node and you're
comparing the key that's stored in the node with the input key.
The likelihood that you'll get a match is very low because that's why you're that's what you're
doing.
You're searching a unique key among 1 billion unique keys.
You're not going to get that match.
So likelihood that you're going to access the next node is very high, right?
So there's a frequently accessed field of the data structure, and there's an extremely infrequently
accessed field of the data structure, rarely accessed.
The problem is those rarely accessed fields.
In this particular case, I guess you're searching for a student with a student ID, let's say, or
name a hash of the name, and you want to get their full name and their school.
I guess it's not a hash of the name.
That doesn't make sense.
So it's ID.
Maybe you want to get their name and school.
The data structure stores all of them in sequence next to each other, right?
That's the node data structure.
And unfortunately, some of them are very frequently accessed.
Some of them are not frequently accessed at all.
So this was not good because other fields, meaning name and school, occupy most of the cache block,
even though they're rarely accessed.
So you want to separate them.
That's the idea.
So this this separated.
The idea is if you separate the rarely accessed field of a data structure and pack them into a
separate data structure, you'll get much better cache locality in this code.
So now you have.
Node structure next and key are frequently accessed and you have a pointer, a small pointer to the
actual data.
That's huge and you're not wasting a lot of cache space.
And you can probably optimise this even more, but this buys you already a lot.
OK, so the general idea is separate hot data from cold data such that they are not in the same cache
block.
That's the general idea.
Identify your hot data, identify your cold data.
Don't put them together, right?
Who should do this becomes a question, right?
Programmer, compiler, hardware.
It's good to think about that.
This is the core of this course.
Basically.
Who should do what?
Everyone can do it at some different cost.
If the programmer does it, that's great, because they've avoided a lot of headache.
If the hardware does it, it's more complex, because now the hardware needs to determine what's hot
and what's not, right?
That's a problem.
Not so easy.
This is semantic information that the programmer can easily figure out.
I think AI can do this.
If it cannot do it, we should kick out that AI.
OK, so this is a good place to stop.
We're going to continue tomorrow with some other ideas and then we'll transition to pre fetching
tomorrow.
See you tomorrow.